<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Querela temporum, or, The danger of the Church of England in a letter from the Dean of ----- to ----- Prebend of.</title>
            <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7679</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13102054</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13102054</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97419</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47752)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97419)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 744:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Querela temporum, or, The danger of the Church of England in a letter from the Dean of ----- to ----- Prebend of.</title>
                  <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Charles Leslie. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: 17 July, 1694.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97419:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Querela Temporum:</hi> OR, THE Danger of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">In a LETTER from the Dean of — to — Prebend of</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LET me employ ſome few Moments in venting my Thoughts to you at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, upon that Subject which has taken up ſo many of our Hours while we were together. The Impreſſion grows ſtronger upon me now that I am alone, and left to the mercy of tormenting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections. The Ruin, which you and I have often bemoaned, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly threatning our Church, is exceedingly magnify'd, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitter'd to me, and muſt be to us all, when we ſadly conſider how we have been led on in our Simplicity, like the Men that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Abſalom,</hi> to be the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our own Deſtruction: And have been engaged ſo far in it, before we were aware, that we are now afraid to look back, though we are aſtoniſh'd to think what the end of all may be.</p>
            <p>I am ſufficiently aſſured, That much the greateſt part of the Clergy have come in to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as you and I have
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97419:2"/>
done, out of a Proſpect to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Church: For if all had ſtuck out, we did dreadfully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prohend that the Presbyterians, conſidering our King's Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Biaſs that way, and their great Merit in the Revolution; (for we were but drawn in, and that late, by a ſeeming neceſſity, and unwillingly.) Our Reluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which we could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal (and at firſt many of us did not deſire to conceal it) was the publick Diſcourſe of the Nation; and ſo much taken notice of, that the Act impoſing the Oaths did not ſuppoſe that all the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy would take them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore left a Proviſion for a certain Number of ſuch of them as ſhould refuſe the Oaths (which I am heartily ſorry has not been ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd;) and thoſe of us who took the Oaths, did it with ſuch Diſtinctions, and Declarations, and Salvos, as made it plain to all the World, That we were not hearty in it, but had a doubting, which is a reſiſting Conſcience. Whereas the Presbyterians, and Common-wealth men, (with ſome Atheiſts and Latitudina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, who call'd themſelves of our Church, though no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than becauſe it was Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Law) were at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the whole Contrivance of the Revolution; and Derided us to ſee into what a Nooſe they had brought us, that we knew not what to Reſolve upon: Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to venture the Reproach of the Nation, by a Change of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples (at leaſt as it would be thought) and to go in to the Government; or to leave K. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> wholy in their hands who brought him in, and to run the hazard of all the Conſequences would follow from his looking upon the Church of <hi>England</hi> as his Enemies, and the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians as the only Church which would ſtick by him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſay, theſe Conſiderations, joyned with his own Inclination, and the little Zeal of the Generality of the Laity for any Church or Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, farther than ſuited with their Intereſts, made us to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend. That if we had not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Oaths, the whole Church might have been over-turn'd all at once; and Presbytery, or Something like it, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t up in its Place, as has been done in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When theſe Conſiderations had determined us in this matter, we were not yet without great Fears what might be the Conſequence, on the other hand, that K. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> could not poſſibly but ſee that our Converſion was Forced, and <hi>Counterfeit,</hi> and would (as ſuch Converſions always do) make us greater Enemies to him than we were before: And that therefore having ſerved his Ends by us, he would watch his time
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97419:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to deſtroy us. That he might compaſs it more eaſily, though may be not ſo <hi>ſpeedily</hi> by our Compliance, having by that made us cheap, and broken our <hi>Authority</hi> with the People. And (O my Friend!) how has he ſucceeded in that! If that was his Deſign. I believe no Age can produce ſo ſudden and great a Change, as 'twixt the Affections of the People to us at this time, and what they were while King <hi>James</hi> was here. I am ſure it is a changed World with us, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may be to others! We were then <hi>Hoſanna'd,</hi> and now it is next door to <hi>Crucify,</hi> while they cannot refrain ſhewing a Concern and Reverence for our <hi>Depriv'd</hi> Brethren. So that it is plain, the Cauſe of our <hi>Contempt</hi> is our Compliance with thoſe who do now <hi>Reproach</hi> us: And it is needleſs to argue, That they are in the ſame Fault, and were firſt in the Fault, and drew or forced us in. They ſay we were their <hi>Guides,</hi> and ought to have led them, and not to have been led by them. They think it no great matter for them to be in a Fault; they think they have a Privilege to be leſs ſtrict than the <hi>Clergy;</hi> and to be ſevere upon our Miſcarriages, ſeems, in ſome ſort, a <hi>Vindication,</hi> at leaſt an <hi>Alleviation</hi> of their own: Which, though a very bad Argument, yet we ſuffer under it.</p>
            <p>And it terrifies me to conſider how much we may yet ſuffer by it, when I reflect that the <hi>Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the People</hi> was made a ſufficient Pretence to Root out Epiſcopacy in <hi>Scotland,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi>'s <hi>Declaration</hi> to that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from the <hi>Hague,</hi> before he came over, bound him to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Church, as then <hi>Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Law,</hi> as well as <hi>ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you think that the <hi>Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the People</hi> can never be made a Pretence againſt <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> you will alter your Opinion when you ſee how little Reaſon there was for that Pretence in <hi>Scotland;</hi> as it is made fully appear in the <hi>Defences</hi> and <hi>Apologies</hi> of the <hi>Epiſcopal Church</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which have been printed Here ſince this <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution:</hi> Which alſo give an Account by what Means and Methods a <hi>Convention</hi> was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained there, which ſhould Vote againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt, <hi>The Inclinations of the People;</hi> take the Account given in one of their <hi>Apologies,</hi> which was Digeſted into <hi>Ten Queſtions,</hi> and printed Here, <hi>An.</hi> 1690. which informs us,</p>
            <p>
               <q>That the Nobility, of the Kingdom, (a very few, not above a Dozen excepted) had all ſworn the <hi>Oath,</hi> commonly called the <hi>Teſt,</hi> wherein all <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natical</hi> Principles and <hi>Covenant
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97419:3"/>
Obligations</hi> were Renounced and Abjured: That not one of <hi>Forty</hi> of the <hi>Gentry,</hi> but had ſworn it alſo; and that not <hi>Fifty</hi> (Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen) in all <hi>Scotland</hi> (out of the <hi>Weſt</hi>) did upon the <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> Granted by King <hi>James, An.</hi> 1687. forſake their <hi>Pariſh Churches</hi> to frequent <hi>Meeting Houſes.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>That the Generality of the <hi>Commons</hi> live in <hi>Cities,</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Towns;</hi> that all who could be of the <hi>Common Council</hi> in ſuch <hi>Corporations,</hi> or were able to follow any <hi>ingenuous Trade,</hi> were obliged to take the <hi>Teſt</hi> (and had generally done it:) That the Clergy ſtood all for <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,</hi> there being of about a <hi>Thouſand</hi> ſcarcely <hi>Twenty</hi> Trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers betwixt the Biſhop and the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Moderator: Which Twenty, together with all the Presbyterian <hi>Preachers,</hi> could not make up the <hi>Fifth</hi> part of ſuch a Number as the other Side amounted to. That in all the <hi>Univerſities,</hi> there were not <hi>Four Maſters, Heads,</hi> or <hi>Fellows,</hi> inclined to <hi>Presbytery:</hi> That the <hi>Colleges</hi> of Juſtice and Phyſick at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> were ſo averſe from it, that the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of them were ready laſt Summer (<hi>viz</hi> 1689.) to take Arms in Defence of their Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Miniſters.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus that Author. And, which is yet a far greater Confirmation of all this to us, his <hi>ſpiteful Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> Adverſary, <hi>G. K.</hi> in his firſt <hi>Vindication of the</hi> (Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian) <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which was writ in anſwer to theſe <hi>Ten Queries,</hi> and printed here in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> 1690. and reprinted at <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> 1691. gives ſuch an Anſwer to this, as is a plain Confeſſion of it. He yields plainly, <hi>all the Gang of the Clergy,</hi> (as he calls them) <hi>except a few:</hi> The <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities,</hi> and <hi>College</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> at leaſt, <hi>as lately ſtated;</hi> and the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality</hi> of the <hi>Burgeſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then he endeavours to make ſome Amuſements as to the ſo <hi>univerſal Defection</hi> (in his Senſe) of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry;</hi> not only in taking the <hi>Anti-Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Teſts,</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second (as <hi>Fear, Intereſt,</hi> and ſuch ſordid Excuſes) but in adhering ſtill to the <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal</hi> Communion after King <hi>James</hi>'s Free <hi>Indulgence,</hi> 1687. for which no <hi>Reaſon</hi> can be given but their own <hi>Inclinations;</hi> the <hi>Favour</hi> from <hi>Court</hi> lying then ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the other ſide.</p>
            <p>In another of theſe <hi>Scots</hi> Tracts, called, <hi>An Account of the preſent Perſecution of the Church of</hi> Scotland, publiſhed 1690. there in the third Letter we read,</p>
            <p>
               <q>That in the Years 1687, and 1688, when the Schiſm was in its Elevation, there were but ſome <hi>Three</hi> or <hi>Four</hi> Presbyterian Meeting houſes erected on the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97419:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>North-ſide</hi> of <hi>Tay, i. e.</hi> in the greater half of the Kingdom; and theſe too very little fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented or encouraged. And that on the <hi>South-ſide</hi> of that River (except in the Five aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated Shires in the <hi>Weſt</hi>) the <hi>Third</hi> Man was never engaged in the Schiſm.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, we are aſſured, as well by theſe Authorities in Print, as by Gentlemen of Senſe and Reputation out of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, the not a <hi>Fifth</hi> or <hi>Sixth</hi> part of the People of <hi>Scotland</hi> did joyn, at that time, with the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that was the Time to ſhew their <hi>Inclinations,</hi> when they might not only do it without <hi>Fear</hi> or <hi>Hazard,</hi> but with all the Proſpects of <hi>Advantage</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How much more conſtant and firm were they to the <hi>Church</hi> in that Kingdom than in this! We did not bear the <hi>Temptation</hi> with ſo little Loſs as they.</p>
            <p>Every <hi>Toleration</hi> and <hi>Indulgence</hi> which has been granted in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> has made much more Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock, and brought more Ruin to the <hi>Church,</hi> than we find this (the moſt dangerous one.) has done in <hi>Scotland.</hi> We have not yet Recover'd from the Miſchief of that in 1672. Before which our <hi>Church</hi> ſeemed to have taken ſome Root, and the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> were wearing much out of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion; many of the Chief of whom, ſeeing a fair likelihood of the perpetuity of the <hi>Church,</hi> were content to ſuffer their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be Educated in our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; though themſelves were aſhamed to comply, after the long Oppoſitions they had made: Which ſhewed they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced both of the <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> and <hi>Expediency</hi> of <hi>Conformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Fire</hi> amidſt <hi>Gun-powder</hi> does not work its deſtructive Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect more <hi>ſuddenly,</hi> than that <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration</hi>-Shook and Rent, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>Over turn'd</hi> our <hi>Church.</hi> The very next Sunday after it was known, the <hi>Churches</hi> in many Places were almoſt quite Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the <hi>Meeting-houſes,</hi> which before were Neglected, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted to by but a few, and thoſe little Regarded, were like Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, when the Sea has broke the Dykes, ſwoln and over-flown in a Moment.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Toleration</hi> upon <hi>Toleration</hi> has brought <hi>Ruin</hi> upon <hi>Ruin</hi> ſince; that we are now Looſe at the very <hi>Roots,</hi> and at the Mercy of every <hi>Wind</hi> and <hi>Wave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by the Accounts we have given us of <hi>Scotland,</hi> they are both more <hi>univerſally</hi> and more <hi>zealouſly</hi> Epiſcopal (eſpecially if you conſider the <hi>Gentry</hi> and <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi>) than the People even in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which there is another ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Inſtance, ſince the <hi>Scots</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97419:4"/>
Treatiſes above quoted were wrote. And that is, That, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſeveral Acts of Parliament there for Aboliſhing <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and Settling the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> Government, and all the fiery Zeal of the <hi>Covenanters</hi> now in Poſſeſſion, yet, through moſt parts of the <hi>North,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of <hi>Scotland,</hi> they, to this day, refuſe to admit the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters</hi> who were ſent to them, or to part with their old <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy,</hi> though they neither <hi>Swear</hi> nor <hi>Pray</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Acts:</hi> But keep them ſtill in Poſſeſſion of their Churches, and Renounce the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>General Aſſembly,</hi> as not being Lawfully Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without <hi>Biſhops.</hi> And have lately publiſhed a Paper in the Name of <hi>the whole Miniſters be-North</hi> Tay; and Twelve Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters at <hi>Aberdeen</hi> gave it, in their own Names, and the Names of all the reſt, to the <hi>Commiſſioners of the General Aſſembly,</hi> wherein they ſtand ſtill by their Depriv'd Biſhops: And as the <hi>Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the (ſaid) Committee of the Aſſembly for the North of</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>to the Privy Council of that Kingdom,</hi> printed now by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in <hi>London</hi> this <hi>October</hi> 94. does expreſs it, They not only <hi>plainly queſtion their Authority, (viz.</hi> of the General Aſſembly) <hi>but the Authority of the Law where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Government of this Church is ſettled.</hi> Nay more, the <hi>Deprived Biſhops</hi> there do not only conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to confer <hi>Holy Orders,</hi> but to fill the <hi>Churches</hi> with thoſe ſo <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd;</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> keep them in. As it is complained of in the ſaid <hi>Repreſentation</hi> which has been Diſperſed by the Presbyterian Faction through the <hi>Coffee-houſes</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> as an Aggravation of the Obſtinacy of the <hi>Scots Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palians</hi> againſt the Government, as they would have it under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; with ſome Queries<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to Diſengage us who have complied with this Government, from any concern for the <hi>Scots Epiſcopalians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the Presbyterian In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt is ſo Low in <hi>Scotland,</hi> how came they of late Years to make ſo great a Noiſe here? Were <hi>They</hi> not the People who formed the Rebellions of <hi>Pent-land Hills,</hi> and <hi>Bothwell Bridge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes. And were ſo eaſily quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as ſhewed the Party to have neither <hi>Intereſt,</hi> nor <hi>Conduct,</hi> nor any other Qualification to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them Conſiderable, beſides that of a <hi>mad Zeal;</hi> like our <hi>Fifth-monarchy Man,</hi> which, grafted upon <hi>Praefervidum Scotorum In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genium, &amp; ad audendum aptum,</hi> produced horrid Aſſaſſinations and deſperate Rebellions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any apprehenſion of <hi>Danger</hi> or <hi>Impoſſibilities:</hi> For <hi>quicquid Scots agunt, valde agunt;</hi> The <hi>Scots</hi> do every thing to the <hi>utmoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97419:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>But how came that Party to gain ſuch a <hi>Convention</hi> there, as to Vote <hi>Epiſcopacy a Grievance,</hi> and contrary to the <hi>Inclinations</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> as it is expreſſed in their <hi>Claim of Right?</hi> This looks like <hi>Management,</hi> or elſe was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good <hi>Luck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was Both in it, as the <hi>Scots Epiſcopal Apologiſts</hi> do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain it to us; and ſhew the Arts of the Miniſters of State who were employ'd in that Affair. That <hi>poor Rabble</hi> of <hi>Covenanters</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> were but the <hi>Tools</hi> who followed the <hi>Cue</hi> given them; they had other help than their own.</p>
            <p>But there were ſome <hi>Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> in that <hi>Juncture,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed more than all the <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Nation was in a violent Ferment; and every one almoſt, except thoſe of the <hi>Cabal,</hi> were unwilling to Dip themſelves in the Firſt Act of a New <hi>Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> nor knowing where it might end. Beſides, the <hi>Epiſcopalians</hi> were, and are ſtill, generally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected towards King <hi>James;</hi> and took as much Pains to keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of that <hi>Convention,</hi> as the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> did to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. All which did not (it could not) prevent many more of the <hi>Epiſcopalians</hi> to be Return'd than of the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> the <hi>Epiſcopalians</hi> being ſo very much the major Number, eſpecially among the better ſort. But ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Epiſcopalians</hi> would not Sit; and many who Sat once, quitted the Houſe, and would appear no more; thinking it culpable to be there. And others were forced away to ſave their Lives from the Fury of the <hi>Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> Rabble, who were arm'd, and made the Guard of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention,</hi> as that extraordinary Man Sir <hi>George Mac Kenzie,</hi> and others. Sir <hi>George Lockhart,</hi> a moſt eminent Lawyer, and who violently oppoſed the <hi>Vacancy</hi> of the <hi>Throne,</hi> was <hi>aſſaſſinated</hi> in the Streets of <hi>Edenburgh;</hi> ſome ſay it was only through a private Pique, but that did not appear to all. The Archbiſhop of <hi>Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gow,</hi> and others of the Clergy, were openly Inſulted in the Streets, and no Remedy. And before the <hi>Convention</hi> was turn'd into a <hi>Parliament,</hi> the Biſhops were, by particular Inſtruments ſent to Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> then <hi>Commiſſioner,</hi> excluded from their Right of Sitting in Parliament.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding of all this purging, they could not get that Parliament ſo model'd, that, if but <hi>Half</hi> of them had Sat, they would ever have aboliſhed <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> or ſet up <hi>Presbytery:</hi> And the <hi>Scots Epiſcopal</hi> Party do vouch, That there were not one <hi>Third</hi> part of the <hi>Members</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, when <hi>Presbytery</hi> was there Eſtabliſh'd.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97419:5"/>I am not now meddling with their Reaſons, why they would not venture to Sit and Vote, at all Hazards. This is only to ſhew that no <hi>Parliament</hi> can be had in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which if Freely Sitting, would Aboliſh <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy:</hi> And that the <hi>Inclinations of the People</hi> cannot be juſtly col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from what was done by that. Leſs than a <hi>Third</hi> part of a Parliament; and that gather'd together by ſtrange <hi>Artifices,</hi> as the <hi>Scotch</hi> Accounts do inform us, as plain as they dare ſpeak, in the Management of their <hi>Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s circular Letter, by which that <hi>Convention</hi> was call'd, being ſent where Preparations were made for its Reception, by ſome Places <hi>later,</hi> and to ſome <hi>not at all,</hi> who yet had Right of Electing Members for Parliament.</p>
            <p>Yet all this could produce no ſuch Appearance in the <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> as would anſwer their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, but they were forced to take into that <hi>Convention</hi> Men Out-lawed for Treaſon, and under other <hi>Legal</hi> Incapacities to Sit in Parliament, by the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts</hi> then in Force; as my Lord <hi>Argile</hi> himſelf, who, before his <hi>Attainder</hi> was taken off by the Parliament, Sat in that <hi>Convention,</hi> and was ſent up <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> with the Tender of the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when they had done all, tryed all <hi>their Ways and Means,</hi> Legal and Illegal, what a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Appearance was it which they were able to procure, at the firſt opening of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> or <hi>Meeting of the Eſtates,</hi> (as they ſtil'd it) which was the 14th of <hi>March,</hi> 1688.</p>
            <p>Of this we have a certain <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,</hi> which is <hi>the Acts and Orders of the Meeting of the Eſtates of the Kingdom of</hi> Scotland, extracted out of their Regiſter, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Authority in <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> 1690.</p>
            <p>There in the Act <hi>Declaring the Meeting of the Eſtates to be a Free and Lawful Meeting,</hi> the 16th of <hi>March,</hi> 1688. all there preſent do ſubſcribe the ſaid Act, and all their Names are printed in the ſaid Act. And there were but <hi>Fifty Burgeſſes</hi> in that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither muſt we reckon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all that ſmall Number it ſelf, as appears by their Fourth <hi>Act,</hi> which is entitled, <hi>An Act for putting the Kingdom in a Poſture of Defence,</hi> the 19th of <hi>March,</hi> 1688. wherein we are told that ſeveral of the <hi>Members</hi> who had ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the former Act, had (in that three Days time) <hi>Deſerted the Meeting of the Eſtates, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd openly to correſpond with the Duke of</hi> Gordon, <hi>ſince the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Intercommuning againſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97419:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
him, and to Retire from this Place</hi> (Edenburgh) <hi>in form of Weirt;</hi> and therefore commands all from Sixteen to Sixty to Arm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Matter was, many of thoſe <hi>Few</hi> who came to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> did not know the Deſigns of the <hi>Managers;</hi> which, aſſoon as they perceived, and that there was a Form'd Party to carry it on, they immediately quit the <hi>Convention,</hi> in <hi>Form of War</hi> (as that Act ſays) and openly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for King <hi>James.</hi> Among theſe was my Lord <hi>Dundee,</hi> who ſat the firſt Day of the <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and his Name is among thoſe who ſubſcribed the firſt Act above-mentioned.</p>
            <p>There were likewiſe <hi>Seven Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> whoſe Names are printed the Firſt of the Subſcribers.</p>
            <p>But their Archbiſhop (of St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi>) as ours, would not come into the <hi>Convention</hi> at all; and it ſeems all the reſt, but the 'bove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Seven,</hi> were of his mind. And that even theſe <hi>Seven</hi> were of thoſe who (as Lord <hi>Dundee</hi> &amp;c) immediately quitted the <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> I ſay, <hi>immediately;</hi> for they ſubſcribed on the 16th of <hi>March,</hi> and the <hi>Hue and Cry</hi> after them was in the 'boveſaid Act of the 19th of the ſame Month</p>
            <p>So that if we are to make any Computation of the <hi>Inclinations of the People</hi> from this <hi>Convention,</hi> it will operate rather againſt the preſent Eſtabliſhment <hi>There,</hi> from the ſmall Appearance of the <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes,</hi> and their great and ſudden <hi>Deſertion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Inclinations of the People</hi> is beſt known by the <hi>Senſe</hi> of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> then it muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, That all along ſince the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> the <hi>Inclinations of the People of</hi> Scotland have been for <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> which has been rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and confirmed by 27 <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> in that Kingdom, (as they are Reckon'd up in theſe <hi>Scotch Epiſcopal</hi> Papers) and where no ſuch Objections, as in the preſent Caſe, can be Alledged. Add to this, what I think a plain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, That the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> dare not truſt a <hi>Free Parliament</hi> in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and that is, that notwithſtanding the great Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of a <hi>Convention</hi> (not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together in the Legal Form) becoming a <hi>Parliament</hi> by a Vote of their own, who were not a <hi>Parliament</hi> before that Vote, or any otherwiſe than by that Vote, by virtue only of the Words themſelves pronounced, when they ſaid <hi>Hoc eſt Parliamentum,</hi> (which ſome have compared to Tranſubſtantiation;) I ſay, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that the <hi>Convention-Parliament</hi> in <hi>England</hi> found it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, for this Reaſon, to have the <hi>Convention-Parliament</hi> diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and a new <hi>Parliament</hi> cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the <hi>King's Writ,</hi> in the uſual Form: Becauſe (as was truly alledg'd) the <hi>Convention</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97419:6"/>
was but in the Nature of a <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunteer,</hi> no Man being obliged to obey the <hi>Circular Letters</hi> of a <hi>Foreign Prince</hi> before he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared <hi>our King.</hi> Nor did his <hi>Circular Letters</hi> import any other than a <hi>Voluntary</hi> Compliance which he expected ſhould be paid to them. And therefore the Subjects would not think their <hi>Liberties</hi> preſerved, unleſs they had the Antient <hi>Freedom</hi> of <hi>Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erved to them, to chuſe Members to ſerve in <hi>Parliament,</hi> knowing before hand that it was to be a <hi>Parliament:</hi> For a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> was new, both Name and Thing; and few underſtood ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Nature of it, or the Ends and Purpoſes for which it was ſummon'd; and to <hi>metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſe</hi> that into a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and then to continue it as ſuch, would be underſtood as a plain <hi>Cheat</hi> to <hi>Trick</hi> the People out of their Votes. Yet all theſe (obvious) Reaſons, and the Example of <hi>England</hi> notwithſtanding, the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Managers in <hi>Scotland</hi> dare not ſummon a new <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but keep on ſtill the old <hi>Convention</hi> with the new Name of a <hi>Parliament:</hi> And though they know that many of the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Perſwaſion <hi>There,</hi> are ſo Zealous, upon the point of the <hi>Government,</hi> that they would not come in, though there were a new <hi>Parliament,</hi> yet the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi> dare not truſt thoſe that might come in, againſt all their own Strength, and all the <hi>Trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> they could Bribe or Frigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to their ſide. For they could never, by their Arts, compaſs ſuch a <hi>Parliament</hi> as would not ſpue out <hi>Presbytery,</hi> as <hi>a Yoke which neither they nor their Fathers were able to bear.</hi> They know it to be utterly impoſſible for them ever again to get ſuch a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Conventioners,</hi> as by their ſecret Intelligence laid (without oppoſition or ſuſpition of the Epiſcopal Party) leap'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and choſe one another, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s <hi>Circular Letters,</hi> which were left wholy to their Management.</p>
            <p>If all this be cauſeleſly alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; let them convince us with the Free and Impartial Election of another <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or give any other Reaſon why they will not, than that they dare not Truſt the <hi>Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the People;</hi> which they know to be the moſt averſe to them, and moſt deſervedly.</p>
            <p>There is another Thing which extreamly ſhews the Weakneſs of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Intereſt there: And that is, That they would never have been able to have planted <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters</hi> there, if the Right of <hi>Patronages</hi> had continued; for there were but very few Gentlemen in that Kingdom, to whom <hi>Advouſons</hi> did belong, who would ever
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97419:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
have <hi>preſented</hi> any <hi>Clerk</hi> that was <hi>Presbyterianly</hi> inclin'd. Therefore all <hi>Patronages</hi> were taken away by Act of <hi>this Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After which one would have expected that the <hi>Free Election</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> ſhould have been ſet up in its full Extent and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative; becauſe this was it for which the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> chiefly contended; they made it to be <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and call'd it, <hi>Chriſt's Legacy</hi> to the <hi>People,</hi> and ſaid it was <hi>Indefeaſible</hi> and <hi>Unalienable</hi> from them.</p>
            <p>But yet they were forced to Diſpenſe with it, <hi>at the Firſt,</hi> and put <hi>the Calling</hi> of <hi>Miniſters</hi> into the hands of the <hi>Presbytery:</hi> For they found the <hi>Inclinations</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> Run againſt them, at leaſt of much the major Number, as well as of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry;</hi> and therefore this Method was <hi>neceſſary (though Antichriſtian,</hi> by their own Principles) for the <hi>firſt</hi> planting of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> (as they ſtile the Preaching of the <hi>Covenant</hi>) in that <hi>Prelatical</hi> Country.</p>
            <p>Neither durſt they, <hi>for the time to come,</hi> truſt the <hi>People</hi> with their <hi>Divine Right</hi> of <hi>Electing</hi> their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> without clogging this <hi>Legacy of Chriſt</hi> (as they call'd it) with ſuch <hi>Limitations</hi> as they could not pretend and to be found in <hi>Scripture.</hi> That none ſhould Vote in the <hi>Election</hi> of <hi>Miniſters</hi> till they firſt ſwore the Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> to K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and ſign the <hi>Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> for which an <hi>Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> is paſſed accordingly.</p>
            <p>Yet, with all theſe Bars and Defences, they found very great Difficulties in planting thoſe Churches, which they have planted with <hi>Presbyterian Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who were ſo few in that Country, That they were forc'd to <hi>Ordain</hi> young Lads from <hi>Shops,</hi> or the <hi>Plow,</hi> as they could get them <hi>Gifted,</hi> without any <hi>Univerſity</hi> Learning: For theſe <hi>Springs,</hi> as themſelves confeſs, were all <hi>corrupted;</hi> that is, in their Senſe, were wholy <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> (as confeſſed in the <hi>Presbyterian Repreſentation</hi> above-told) they have got little or no Footing to this Day. In which parts they are ſo ſtrongly <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> that, as I read in a very accurate and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Account of the Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings there about the <hi>Convention</hi> time. <hi>It were no hard Task,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to give a juſt Account how</hi> it only happen'd <hi>that there was ſo much as one</hi> Northern <hi>Member (who was not ſuch by Birth)</hi> of the Presbyterian <hi>Perſwaſion in the Meeting of the Eſtates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there can be no ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, as their preſerving their <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy,</hi> and keeping out the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97419:7"/>
               <hi>Acts of Parliament;</hi> and that the <hi>Privy Council</hi> (which has <hi>There</hi> almoſt the Power of a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> in the Intervals of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament) have interpoſed their Authority to Ratify the Decrees of the <hi>Presbytery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, even in their own Dear <hi>Weſt Country,</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> found ſo much Difficulty, in ſome Places, particularly near <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> to perfect their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> that they were forced to fill a Church there with <hi>Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> to fright the People from Singing the <hi>Doxology,</hi> from which they could not otherwiſe be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. Was not this ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like Dragooning! But I go on.</p>
            <p>It may be thought Strange (Things being as here told) what Ground or Pretence could be found for Repreſenting <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy</hi> to be contrary to the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of theſe People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And herein appears a <hi>Subtile</hi> but very wicked <hi>Politick</hi> of the <hi>Managers</hi> then at <hi>Helm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They firſt had Arms put into the hands of the <hi>mad Cameronian</hi> true <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Rabble of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and then ſet them on to <hi>Mob</hi> the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy,</hi> in thoſe <hi>Fanatical</hi> Shires, which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted in a moſt <hi>Savage</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: And from thence they <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented</hi> the <hi>Inclinations of the People</hi> to be <hi>irreconcilable</hi> to <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy.</hi> And upon Enquiry, I cannot find that there is any now, who inſiſt longer upon that common Place of the <hi>Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the People</hi> of <hi>Scotland:</hi> It, like ſome other Stories has ſerv'd its Turn, except one <hi>Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant,</hi> who had Presbyterian Education, and from his Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was taught to Hate and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> who has Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Church in <hi>Eaſt Lothian,</hi> and was Expell'd neither by Force, nor by the Rabble, nor any Sentence of any <hi>Presbyterian Judicature;</hi> but fearing that the Gentry of his Pariſh, to whom he was always moſt Diſagreable, would lay hold of the preſent Opportunity to turn him out, when their <hi>Inclinations</hi> was made the Standard, he thought it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to leave the Place with leſs Diſgrace.</p>
            <p>And he is now encouraged by a certain Miniſter of State, to propagate that Notion here in <hi>England,</hi> that the Temper of the People in <hi>Scotland</hi> is againſt <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> and moſt inclin'd to <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery.</hi> And the Rabbling of the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy</hi> in ſome parts of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> is all the Argument.</p>
            <p>This is all, and every bit of, the Ground the <hi>Convention,</hi> or any other, had to Repreſent the <hi>Inclinations of the People</hi> as averſe to <hi>Prelacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor had they had this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence it ſelf, <hi>if All</hi> the <hi>People</hi> even in thoſe ſame <hi>Fanatical</hi> Shires,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97419:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
had been left to their own <hi>Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations:</hi> For when the <hi>College of Juſtice</hi> in <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and others (in whom remain'd what was left of any Right to <hi>Govern,</hi> after King <hi>James</hi> quitted <hi>England,</hi> and before any other <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> was Fram'd) took Arms againſt this <hi>murdering Rabble,</hi> in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy,</hi> and <hi>Themſelves,</hi> (for ſuch an <hi>Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> threatened <hi>All</hi>) a <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> came out from the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> commanding <hi>All</hi> to lay down their Arms. This was obey'd by the <hi>College of Juſtice,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: (as thinking it tending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Peace and Settlement:) But not at all by the others Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they knew it was not inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt <hi>Them.</hi> And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly made uſe of it (their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies being thus Diſarm'd) to commit more inſolent Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties againſt the <hi>Clergy</hi> than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>And in Reward for their Zeal, were not only continu'd in <hi>Arms,</hi> but made the Guard of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention,</hi> which ſoon after met, under their <hi>Gracious Protection,</hi> and acted by their <hi>Influence. Theirs!</hi> who thought it <hi>Merit,</hi> and the <hi>Cauſe of God,</hi> to <hi>aſſaſſinate</hi> the Archbiſhop of St. <hi>Andrews</hi> on the High-way; and declared it their Principle to <hi>murther,</hi> by whatever means, every <hi>Biſhop;</hi> and every <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> who took their part. <hi>Theirs!</hi> who for <hi>Declaring</hi> and <hi>Acting</hi> purſuant to ſuch <hi>Diabolical</hi> Principles (though <hi>All</hi> the Genuine Effects of their common Mother the Covenant) were (out of meer Shame) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own'd by other their <hi>Phariſee</hi> Brethren of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> for throwing off the <hi>Sheeps Cloathing,</hi> and acting the <hi>Wolf</hi> ſo plainly and above Board: For <hi>Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> not only the <hi>Simplicity</hi> of the <hi>Dove,</hi> but the <hi>Prudence</hi> of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> of whom they retain'd nothing but the <hi>Sting.</hi> And who could have any other thought than that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> was Reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved only for <hi>Execution,</hi> when it was placed under ſuch <hi>Camero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Guards?</p>
            <p>And when the moſt Violent and Bigotted <hi>Phanaticks</hi> were made the Principal <hi>Miniſters of State?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But who was it choſe <hi>thoſe Miniſters?</hi> That muſt be the <hi>Kings Inclination.</hi> He choſe them according to <hi>his own Inclinations;</hi> and then took their Word, for the <hi>Inclinations of the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And can we think his <hi>Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> are different in <hi>England,</hi> otherwiſe than as <hi>Reaſon of State</hi> moves him?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Experiment</hi> muſt Begin in <hi>Scotland:</hi> And according to the Succeſs <hi>there,</hi> the Meaſures are to be taken <hi>here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And do we not ſee the ſame <hi>Meaſures</hi> taken <hi>here,</hi> though
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97419:8"/>
perhaps in ſomewhat a ſlower March?</p>
            <p>Has not a certain great Man, of an Intereſt very contrary to that of the <hi>Church;</hi> one whoſe Treachery towards <hi>it</hi> has made him an irreconcilable and inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate Enemy to <hi>it,</hi> been brought from behind the Curtain, where he acted ſo much Miſchief un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen, and now in a manner pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly ſet upon the Stage? Has he not acted indeed as one deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, and that knows himſelf unſafe under any thing but a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick</hi> Party eſtabliſhed in both Kingdoms; as one that can hope for no forgiveneſs from another Intereſt which he has ſo perfidiouſly treated, and where all thoſe that are leading and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected Men know him ſo well, have felt him, and are ſure nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be impoſed upon by him more, nor ever to forget what he has done to the Church, and againſt them as the Patrons of it? Have we not ſeen how things have turn'd ſince this? Was not not the whole Miniſtry changed to bring in that Gang? How had ſuch a Fellow as <hi>Jack Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,</hi> or <hi>Somers,</hi> been hoiſted upon a ſudden where they now are, but meerly on this Accompt, that they only were thought deep enough in a <hi>Fanatick</hi> Intereſt to ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry on this Deſign, and to ſupport this new Foundation of ſome great Men, who muſt make good what they are engaged in, and ſecure themſelves by <hi>thorow work,</hi> or ſoon fall, and come to that end which they deſerve?</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Nottingham,</hi> a Man who they offer to reproach with nothing but his Fidelity to <hi>our Church,</hi> and his conſtant Care of its Intereſt; one of ſuch allow'd Capacity, Vigilancy, and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable Diligence in his Office, and of ſuch known Fidelity to the Crown and this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſuch a Man as this we ſee of a ſudden removed, and without any reaſon given (but what is thus plainly left for any one to infer) thruſt out of his Employment, diſgraced, and driven at as one ready to be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached; which Deſign it was no great wonder to ſee carried on under ſuch as could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their being themſelves Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached, were the Government as it ought to be, or the <hi>Church</hi> reſtored to that Place which it ought to have, and which one may very juſtly ſay <hi>it muſt have,</hi> unleſs <hi>Monarchy</hi> be deſign'd for Ruin.</p>
            <p>The Juſtification which the Parliament laſt Year gave to the <hi>Admirals,</hi> after the moſt mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and falſe Aſperſions imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, did not hinder their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thrown out with all the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace that could be put upon them. At leaſt thoſe Two that were the Chief, and chiefly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97419:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
noted for their Firmneſs to the <hi>Church,</hi> were ſo ſerved. What are the reſt of the Changes in the <hi>Admiralty,</hi> and every where elſe? What are the <hi>Ruſſels,</hi> and the <hi>Whartons,</hi> that are now in ſuch Credit, and have their Friends every where advanced? Who knows not the <hi>Cabal</hi> at <hi>Court,</hi> and that Lord <hi>Sh</hi>— who firſt went out of Court upon this bottom, and is now returned again upon the ſame, is of this Confederacy; and both too early, and too deeply, engaged with this Party to be a Head or a leading Man any where elſe?</p>
            <p>Our Friends are ſhifted out apace. And now openly, and above Board, there have been new Regulations of all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Militia</hi> through <hi>England;</hi> of the <hi>Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> the <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> &amp;c. on purpoſe to fill all with the <hi>Fanatical</hi> and <hi>Whiggiſh</hi> Tribe; who have out-grown us, and are too many for us, in all Places of <hi>Truſt</hi> and <hi>Profit.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Either profeſſed and open Diſſenters, or the more dangerous Church Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks; who keep in our Communion no otherways than as Spies; who ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule us, and do us all the ill Offices that is in their Power; and but watch an Opportunity to deſtroy us, and our Conſtitution. Of ſuch Principles (moſt Iniquous to the Church) are the preſent <hi>Attorney</hi> and <hi>Solicitor General,</hi> and almoſt all the King's Council, as <hi>Wi. Williams,</hi> Serjeant <hi>Tompſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hawles,</hi> &amp;c. Baron <hi>Letchmore,</hi> Baron <hi>Turton,</hi> that little Baron Tell Clock Mr. <hi>Bradbury,</hi> and others upon the Bench. And with <hi>Ruſſel</hi> are joyn'd in the Commiſſion of the <hi>Admiralty</hi> that virulent Whig Col. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten;</hi> and <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Hublon,</hi> two rigid Fanaticks. Such are <hi>Montague</hi> and <hi>Smith,</hi> two of the Lords Commiſſioners of the <hi>Treaſury,</hi> indefatigable Sticklers for the Whig Party. <hi>Papillion</hi> and <hi>Mayne,</hi> in the <hi>Victualling-Office;</hi> and <hi>Hill</hi> of the <hi>Navy-Office.</hi> Sir <hi>J. Foach,</hi> Sir <hi>Steph. Evans, Ed. Clark, Tho. Hall, J. Danvers,</hi> (the only Son of a Regicide) and <hi>Foot Onſlow</hi> in the <hi>Exciſe. Parkhurſt, Murray, Vernon,</hi> and <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal,</hi> in the <hi>Prize Office.</hi> Col. <hi>Kirby, Shepherd,</hi> and <hi>Welwood,</hi> in that for the Sick and Wounded. <hi>Aſhurſt,</hi> in that of the Hackny Coaches; and <hi>Franklin</hi> in the <hi>Poſt-Office.</hi> And in the <hi>Cuſtom-houſe,</hi> Sir <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Young,</hi> Mr. <hi>Chedwick,</hi> Sir <hi>Patience Ward,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Clayton.</hi> And a long, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in other Offices and Places of Truſt through the Kingdom, too long to be here inſerted. The Whig, and (I know not which to ſay) Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural or Unnatural Libertine, the Lord <hi>Sidney,</hi> now Earl of <hi>Rumney,</hi> is made Maſter of the <hi>Ordnance,</hi> and Governour of the <hi>Cinque Ports,</hi> and <hi>Dover Caſtle,</hi> &amp;c. And Whig, Sir <hi>Tho. Littleton,</hi> is under him in the <hi>Ordnance.</hi> Lord <hi>Cuts,</hi> an Atheiſtical Whig, is made Governour of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le of <hi>Wight.</hi> Theſe, and many more, are the Men now employ'd.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97419:9"/>Little needy Fellows are put into Employments of greateſt Honour and Import, ſo they be but Fanatick <hi>enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Johnſton</hi> Secretary for <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who the other day meerly for Bread travell'd with Sir <hi>Rob. Barnard,</hi> his Condition being then very neceſſitous, though he is now one of the chief <hi>Mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> in both Kingdoms. His only Merit is the new faſhion'd <hi>Theiſm,</hi> grafted upon <hi>rigid Fanaticiſm;</hi> the laſt of which he derived from his Father, that Arch Rebel <hi>Wariſton,</hi> who was <hi>Clerk</hi> in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary to the <hi>Presbyterian General Aſſembly</hi> in his time, and as fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious againſt the <hi>Mitre</hi> as the <hi>Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such another is that Infamous <hi>James Stuart,</hi> an <hi>Inveterate Rebel,</hi> and pardon'd by King <hi>James,</hi> now Knighted <hi>(forſooth!)</hi> and fills the Place of Lord <hi>Advocate,</hi> which anſwers to that of <hi>Attorny General</hi> here; but of greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Intereſt in the <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſtairs,</hi> a <hi>Super-presbyterian,</hi> that is, a <hi>Cameronian</hi> Preacher, attends K. <hi>William</hi>'s Perſon, both at <hi>home</hi> and <hi>abroad,</hi> like a Jewel in his Ear: <hi>We</hi> make a Show in the <hi>Chapel,</hi> but <hi>He</hi> Exerciſes the Office of <hi>Confeſſor</hi> in the <hi>Cloſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Advice is taken in all the Spiritual Promotions of our <hi>Church;</hi> and we feel the Effects of it very ſenſibly.</p>
            <p>We ſee among the new made Biſhops thoſe who were former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Fanatical</hi> Preachers; and thoſe who, of all our Number, are leaſt Zealous for the <hi>Church,</hi> and moſt <hi>Latitudinarian,</hi> for a <hi>Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> and a <hi>Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with our <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi> The <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> himſelf has put on a ſtrange <hi>Moderation</hi> that way.</p>
            <p>The Tide runs ſtrong both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> towards a <hi>Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> Level. And the Pattern of the <hi>Scotiſh Reformation</hi> ſtares us in the Face, more Glaringly than in 42.</p>
            <p>And let us remember, That the <hi>Covenant</hi> (now Rampant in <hi>Scotland</hi>) obliges them to carry on the work of that Reformation in <hi>England,</hi> as well as in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as they did before: And they have the <hi>Impudence</hi> to pray <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly</hi> for it now in their <hi>Churches,</hi> for our <hi>Converſion</hi> (as they call it) from <hi>Prelacy,</hi> which they call <hi>Popery;</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> that is, our <hi>Liturgy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet their <hi>Agents</hi> there would make us believe, That they intend no Alteration of our Conſtitution in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But are we to be ſo Deceived now? Have we never been De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97419:9"/>
by them, in the ſame manner, before? How often did they proteſt to Marquiſs <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton,</hi> Commiſſioner for King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, That they did not intend to aboliſh <hi>Epiſcopacy? [Large Declaration,</hi> 114, 115. 69. <hi>and</hi> 173.]</p>
            <p>And they uſed to perſwade the Scrupulous, That they might take the Covenant without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In their Anſwer to the Fourth Reply of the Doctors of <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen,</hi> they ſay, <hi>You will have all the Covenanters againſt their Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and whether they will or not, to Diſallow and Condemn the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of</hi> Perth, <hi>and Epiſcopal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.— But it is known to many Hundreds, that the Words were pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely conceived for Satisfaction of ſuch as were of your Judgment, that we might all joyn in one Heart and Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They had <hi>Lower</hi> and <hi>Higher</hi> Senſes of this <hi>Oath.</hi> Any thing to get you once within their <hi>Circle;</hi> and though they preſs the Obligation of it upon all alike, like the Artifice of ſome of the <hi>Romiſh Emiſſaries,</hi> who, to a Perſon tenacious of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed</hi> Doctrins, repreſent the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing differing from us in <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals,</hi> as they call them; and will let him keep all the Opinions they can't perſwade him from, only be reconciled to the <hi>Church,</hi> to avoid <hi>Schiſm:</hi> But when he is once in, then there is no ſtop, they can Drive him to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. They bring in <hi>many Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds</hi> of their <hi>private Doctors</hi> for the <hi>lower Senſe</hi> of their <hi>General Councils;</hi> as their <hi>Spawn</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> do leave their <hi>many Hundreds</hi> of <hi>private Perſons,</hi> who they at firſt pretended knew their Minds in wording of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> to be much lower than the <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Oath</hi> ſeemed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</p>
            <p>But yet they would never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards allow any ſuch <hi>private Interpretations,</hi> as the true and natural Senſe of the <hi>Oath.</hi> But boldly charged them of <hi>Perjury,</hi> who in the leaſt Tittle departed from them.</p>
            <p>And how many Oaths and Proteſtations had we from our <hi>Engliſh Parliament</hi> in 42. That they never intended the Aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion either of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> or the <hi>Liturgy?</hi> But, on the contrary, they expreſſed a great Zeal for Both; till they had got a Set of <hi>Fanatical Miniſters</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> and <hi>They</hi> then ſoon introduced <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the ſame Kidney in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And did not they <hi>then</hi> ſet up the <hi>Inclinations of the People</hi> on their ſide? And did not they carry it?</p>
            <p>And yet they had not half the Pretence as now. For, before that Rebellion, <hi>England</hi> had been
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97419:10"/>
long in the quiet Poſſeſſion of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> without almoſt any Grumbling againſt it; and that but of ſo ſmall and inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a Party, as did not ſeem worth notice. Theſe Monſters were Bred, and Grew up, in the <hi>Storm:</hi> But ſince the <hi>Over-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of that <hi>Schiſmatical Rebellion;</hi> our Land has been Fertile of as many <hi>Heterogenious</hi> Productions, as the Mud of <hi>Nilus</hi> leaves upon <hi>Egypt.</hi> There are almoſt as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny various <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Armies</hi> of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> now, as there were ſingle <hi>Mutineers</hi> at that time.</p>
            <p>And oh! the Difference! <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had a <hi>King</hi> then who was Bred from his Childhood in the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Communion, and <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> for it, even to <hi>Martyrdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our preſent King had the Misfortune (to himſelf, and to us) to be Educated under the <hi>Geneva</hi> Model, made <hi>Eraſtian</hi> in <hi>Holland:</hi> And it cannot be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, That the Alteration of his preſent <hi>Circumſtances</hi> have wrought as great a Change in his <hi>Principles:</hi> That would be (if not a <hi>Miracle</hi>) to ſuppoſe him to be wholy <hi>Latitudinarian,</hi> and indifferent to all <hi>Religions;</hi> at leaſt as to <hi>Church Government,</hi> which is the Point <hi>We</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for.</p>
            <p>But (alaſs!) the Meaſures he has taken in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>here</hi> too (as faſt as it can go) has ſadly undeceived us; and given Demonſtration, That he is as zealous for his <hi>Religion,</hi> as any other <hi>King</hi> at leaſt.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, it is evident, That King <hi>James</hi> never took more Pains to place ſuch <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> as were, if not <hi>Popiſhly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected,</hi> yet leaſt Inclin'd againſt it, than K. <hi>William</hi> has done, by the ſame Method, in Favour of <hi>Presbytery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there is yet a farther Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for him to put himſelf In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely into their hands as ſoon as he poſſibly can; and that is, That he can never Truſt to <hi>Us.</hi> He ſees (we cannot keep it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd) that much the major Number of the <hi>Swearing Clergy</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and thoſe who are upon the Foundations of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities, are <hi>Jacobites</hi> in their Hearts; and many of them have not the Continence to keep it to themſelves, but Blab it where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they go: Inſomuch that the Nation has it by the End, That we are all <hi>Jacobites;</hi> at leaſt, we are all (except a very few) <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected,</hi> and that is equal to <hi>Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> in the Argument I am now upon.</p>
            <p>Well, but whatever are the <hi>King</hi>'s Inclinations or Deſigns as to the <hi>Church,</hi> we Truſt to the <hi>Inclinations</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> that they are all for <hi>Us;</hi> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>his</hi> Intereſt will perſwade him to comply with <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:97419:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Firſt, We have many and abundant Inſtances, ſince the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Revolution, how far he can prevail with the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> at leaſt with their <hi>Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> in the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> to comply with <hi>his</hi> Intereſt or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We have found the <hi>Inclinations of the People</hi> turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, in the late Rebellion againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, when they were much more uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly for us than they are at preſent.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Inclinations of the People</hi> may be <hi>pretended,</hi> when it is not <hi>True,</hi> as we have ſeen in <hi>Scotland:</hi> And a Set of <hi>Fanatical</hi> Miniſters of State may ſet up ſuch a <hi>Pretence</hi> when they pleaſe. Pretences are the eaſieſt found Things in the World; as we ſay, It it no hard matter to <hi>find a Stick to beat a Dog.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But towards making the moſt True and Impartial Computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that can be, as to the <hi>Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the People</hi> in <hi>England</hi> at this Day, in reference to <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,</hi> and the <hi>preſent Eſtabliſh'd Church;</hi> Let us firſt take a View of the <hi>Nation</hi> in the General, and particularly of <hi>London,</hi> (and that not only as to the Differences betwixt <hi>Us</hi> and the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith regard likewiſe to their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations</hi> as Divided betwixt <hi>Us</hi> and our <hi>Deprived</hi> Fathers and Brethren,) then of the Two Houſes of <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons:</hi> And theſe are the ſureſt Steps I know whereby to compute the <hi>Inclinations</hi> of the People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to take a General View of <hi>England;</hi> we ſadly find, That the Reverence to <hi>Religion</hi> in the General is mightily abated, and, amongſt very many, quite loſt. And therefore a Diſpute only about <hi>Church Government</hi> will be thought of very little Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence with theſe.</p>
            <p>There is a Spirit of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> gone out into this Land, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially amongſt the Gentry of the firſt Magnitude; and Books are daily publiſhed, and greedily bought up, to render what they call <hi>Prieſt Craft,</hi> the Object of all Peoples <hi>Hate</hi> and <hi>Contempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And will thoſe who have no <hi>Regard</hi> for <hi>Religion,</hi> have any <hi>Reverence</hi> for <hi>Church-men?</hi> Thoſe, who think <hi>Them</hi> and their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion Uſeleſs, and a Cheat? And conſequently an unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary <hi>Burden</hi> and <hi>Charge</hi> to the People, and therefore neceſſary to be removed. That they are kept up only by the Folly and Superſtition of a few <hi>Bigots,</hi> who dare not <hi>Think</hi> out of the Road of their Forefathers; whom theſe <hi>Vertuoſos</hi> have taken all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Pains to undeceive, and convert them to the generous <hi>Latitude</hi> and <hi>Largeneſs</hi> of <hi>Thought</hi> (as they call it) That if they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97419:11"/>
cannot get rid of <hi>All</hi> Religions, to be <hi>Indifferent</hi> towards <hi>All;</hi> and to look no farther than the <hi>Legal</hi> Eſtabliſhment; or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of <hi>Religion</hi> no otherwiſe than as it is part of our <hi>Property,</hi> made ſo by the <hi>Laws,</hi> and which therefore may be Alter'd by the <hi>Laws:</hi> At leaſt, as to <hi>Church-Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how can we deny this, who have allowed of <hi>Lay-Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, Brother, I muſt tell you, That this <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> Principle has ſtrangely prevailed even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our <hi>Clergy;</hi> chiefly of the <hi>firſt Form,</hi> in whoſe hands all our Concernments lie, and the publick Affairs of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now as to the Third Eſtate of Men in the Kingdom, the Commonalty; What can we expect from them, but to be led by their <hi>Clergy,</hi> their <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry?</hi> And do we not find it ſo? Some think our Party great from the Appearance in our <hi>Churches</hi> here in <hi>London.</hi> But the <hi>Churches</hi> in <hi>London</hi> will not hold the Tenth part of the <hi>People</hi> in <hi>London:</hi> And therefore a ſmall Proportion of the People will make a great Shew in our <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> Beſides, the Generality of the People do give themſelves a Latitude to go to <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> indifferently; and ſince both are now equally Tolerated by the Law, they do not think it a Fault, at leaſt they cannot be <hi>Cenſured,</hi> nor they think ſo much as juſtly <hi>Blamed</hi> for it. I know ſeveral, even of the firſt Rank of the <hi>Gentry,</hi> who not only go to hear Sermons, but Receive the <hi>Communion,</hi> both at <hi>Church,</hi> and at the <hi>Meetings.</hi> This is a ſtrange proſtitution of our <hi>Diſcipline<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> But we muſt not now pretend to <hi>Power,</hi> if we can <hi>Live,</hi> we muſt <hi>let Live.</hi> Thoſe Days of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> are over: We now ſeem to be in the Height of the <hi>Laodicean</hi> State.</p>
            <p>Again. Many of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> Party (who canot love our Conſtitution) come to <hi>Church;</hi> ſome to preſerve their Places, and in reverence to the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Teſt;</hi> others, for meer <hi>Faſhion ſake;</hi> and not a Few, on purpoſe to Watch, and Report, and find Objections, or to make them.</p>
            <p>By theſe means our Churches are fill'd. But when we have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted All, but who came hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of a pure Principle of <hi>Religion:</hi> And again, when we have ſubdivided from theſe, thoſe who think not that <hi>Religion</hi> conſiſts in <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> or any Form of <hi>Church-Government,</hi> but look only to the <hi>Devotional</hi> part, which they may think might be preſerved under any other <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> as well as that of <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> though they may (perchance) like that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97419:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Beſt, as being moſt uſed to it. (All who were ſtrictly princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled in the <hi>Divine Right</hi> of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> and conſequently its <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependence</hi> upon the <hi>State,</hi> are gone from us into the Separate Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the <hi>Depriv'd Biſhops:</hi> And many, though they keep in our Communion, are with them in their Hearts.)</p>
            <p>I ſay, when we have ſubſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thoſe who make their Appearance at our <hi>Churches</hi> upon ſolemn Occaſions, <hi>All,</hi> except thoſe who would be content to ſtruggle for <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and for us now in Poſſeſſion, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>Depriv'd Biſhops,</hi> to ſtruggle for us, as the <hi>Epiſcopal Laity</hi> have done in <hi>Scotland</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Laws</hi> in Being, and the <hi>Reigning Miniſters,</hi> to the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of their <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Eſtates;</hi> when <hi>All</hi> but ſuch as theſe are ſubſtracted from our Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I am afraid we ſhall have but little Reaſon to Boaſt of our Numbers.</p>
            <p>And though Mens coming to <hi>Church</hi> is no ſure Sign of their being true <hi>Church-men;</hi> yet their Forſaking, or Neglecting the <hi>Church,</hi> is a certain Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they are otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Add to this, a very <hi>Fatal Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemma</hi> in which the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have Caught us, and have Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd it amongſt the <hi>People,</hi> to our no ſmall Prejudice. For if we ſtick to <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> in the High Senſe, as it is contain'd in the <hi>Homily againſt Rebellion,</hi> we muſt condemn what we have done, and what we ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to do. But if we call that an Error, then we own that our <hi>Church</hi> has been all along, before this Revolution, a falſe Guide; and that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have taught the Truth, in this point of Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine: And then the People them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves make the Application, that it is ſafer truſting to <hi>Them</hi> than to <hi>Us</hi> in other Doctrines. For, ſay they, the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> never went over to you, in any of their <hi>Doctrines;</hi> but you have gone over to <hi>them</hi> in This, which you Formerly preſſed as Poſſitively and Zealouſly as any other <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> nay, more than moſt others, and as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſibly neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And will a People thus preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced againſt us, be <hi>zealous</hi> for us? Zealous againſt the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to whom we have at laſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, in our ſo long boaſted <hi>Characteriſtical Diſcrimination</hi> of <hi>Paſſive Obedience?</hi> How ſhall we retract all the hard Words we have given them for oppoſing that <hi>Doctrine</hi> which we now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs! For uſing thoſe ſame <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions</hi> which we now ſet up! And what Argument can we find to perſwade the People that we may not Deceive them in other <hi>Doctrines,</hi> as well as in this? Why
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97419:12"/>
they ſhould Adhere to <hi>us,</hi> againſt the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> who have kept their Ground, and not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted their own Doctrines?</p>
            <p>Indeed our Caſe <hi>here</hi> is very difficult. It is needleſs <hi>now</hi> to Blame the Preaching of <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> ſo high in the former Reigns: The Fault is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, we cannot deny it; and we muſt ſuffer under the Shame of it. And we have loſt exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly in the <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the People <hi>now</hi> towards us, upon that account. They look upon us <hi>Inconſtant,</hi> and <hi>Time-ſerving.</hi> And that Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a <hi>Clergy-man</hi> muſt forfeit all Mens Value and Eſteem for him: And conſequently for <hi>All</hi> that <hi>Clergy,</hi> or <hi>Church,</hi> of whom they have conceived ſuch an Opinion.</p>
            <p>And tho you and I can vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate our ſelves as to the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> in former Times; What is this to all that Generality of the Clergy who were never Weary, nor would give over upon that Subject? Who found it in every Text they could meet with? And preſſed it oftener, and more patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, than any Article of the Creed?</p>
            <p>And though we did not preach for it, yet we did not preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. We let it go: Which the People think we ſhould not have done, if we thought it to be an Errour; and ſo <hi>Fatal</hi> a one as it muſt be, if it can be an Errour. They call this <hi>Time-ſerving</hi> in us <hi>then,</hi> as much as in the others <hi>now:</hi> And then our Subſcriptions to the <hi>Homilies,</hi> and Reading the <hi>Declaration</hi> of its not being Lawful, <hi>upon any Pretence,</hi> to take Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are thrown in our Diſh.</p>
            <p>And it is needleſs <hi>here</hi> to inſiſt upon our Defences; for the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry we are <hi>now</hi> making, is not the <hi>truth</hi> or <hi>untruth</hi> of the Caſe, but only as to the <hi>Inclinations of the People<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> that is, How <hi>They</hi> take it, not how it is in it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Thus far we have obſerved concerning the <hi>People</hi> in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and in <hi>London:</hi> But let us now come nearer, and obſerve their Countenance in the Great <hi>Repreſentative</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> The <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Here,</hi> like drawing near to an ill Daub'd Landskip, the Strokes appear more Groſs and Diſproportion'd,</p>
            <p>What a contemptible Figure do our Biſhops now make in the <hi>Houſe of Lords!</hi> It was never ſo known before. <hi>No! Never!</hi> They are obliged either to quit their Seats in that Houſe, or to bear the Railery of the <hi>Lay-Lords</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Day, who think them a <hi>Dead Weight</hi> amongſt the <hi>Peers;</hi> of whom the greateſt part would be glad to be rid of them, not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97419:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
only out of <hi>their Houſe,</hi> but out of the Nation.</p>
            <p>And it may here be noted, That <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> was in greater Perfection, and more primitive Independency, in <hi>Scotland,</hi> than with us here in <hi>England;</hi> and likewiſe as much fortified by the Civil Law, and ſet higher in the <hi>State,</hi> than (ſince the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>) in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Clergy,</hi> there, are a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct <hi>Eſtate</hi> by themſelves, and preferr'd, in all things, to the <hi>Temporal Nobility:</hi> For not only the two <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> (as in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>) but every one of the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> do Sign before all the whole <hi>Temporal Lords;</hi> as may be ſeen in the Act above-mention, 16th of <hi>March,</hi> 1688 where all the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> ſubſcribed their Names; and the Seven <hi>Biſhops</hi> who was there, did ſubſcribe before Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> (though then Preſident of the <hi>Convention</hi>) and all the <hi>Lay-Lords.</hi> And their Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are thus Indorſed in the ſaid Act: <hi>The</hi> Clergy <hi>and</hi> Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <hi>ſubſcribed thus.</hi> When the Rolls in Parliament are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led over, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> are <hi>all</hi> firſt called.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Biſhops</hi> chuſe <hi>Lords of the Articles</hi> out of the <hi>Temporal</hi> Eſtate of the <hi>Lay Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all things, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> there are diſtinguiſhed more plainly as a <hi>Separate</hi> Eſtate, and the <hi>Firſt</hi> of the <hi>Three Eſtates,</hi> than with us.</p>
            <p>But they have a yet much greater Advantage above our <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> in their <hi>Eccleſiaſtiacal</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
            <p>They have no <hi>Prohibitions</hi> from the <hi>Secular</hi> Courts to hang up their <hi>Excommunications,</hi> or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle in their <hi>Spiritual Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Biſhops</hi> there are Abſolute Judges of the Fitneſs of <hi>Clerks,</hi> preſented to them for <hi>Livings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Nor give any Account hereof to the <hi>Secular Courts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay more; they can Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplant any <hi>Prieſt</hi> in their <hi>Dioceſe</hi> from one <hi>Pariſh</hi> to another, as they ſhall judge their Labours to be more profitable in one Place than another, and there lies no Remedy for the <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſo Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplanted from the <hi>Secular</hi> Courts; of which I have been told In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Civil Law</hi> has made no ſuch Inrodes upon the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Authority in <hi>Scotland</hi> as in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and therefore our <hi>Biſhops</hi> can plead no Exemption (more than they) from being caſt out of the <hi>Church,</hi> whenever a <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> ſhall pleaſe to have it ſo.</p>
            <p>There is, as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſays, but one <hi>Epiſcopate</hi> in the whole World, of which every Biſhop partakes Severally, yet in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. <hi>Epiſcopatus unus eſt, cujus a ſingulus, in ſolidum, pars tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Cyp. <hi>de unit. Eccleſ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:97419:13"/>Therefore the Caſe of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> at preſent, is not only <hi>proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Utalegon</hi> to us; but 'tis our own very Caſe, upon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bottom of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>For if we give up the <hi>Jus Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> we muſt yield it alſo as to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And then we are wholy <hi>Precarious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if in the <hi>Church,</hi> much leſs let us think that Biſhops are ſo eſſential to <hi>Parliaments,</hi> but that (as in <hi>England</hi> in 42. and <hi>now</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi>) they may be Diſpenc'd with.</p>
            <p>And the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Lords,</hi> have, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeveral Occaſions, minded them of their <hi>Frailty:</hi> And that what has been done, may be done, as well in this as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Things. But more than all this, both Houſes of <hi>Commons</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> have ſhewn their Love to us, and high Regard of our Conſtitution, in that they have diveſted us of all our <hi>Authority</hi> over the People, by their unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Act of Indulgence to all Sorts and Sizes of <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> and commanding that the <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Courts ſhall have no Power to proceed againſt any of them. And giving Power to the <hi>Juſtices of Peace,</hi> at their Seſſions, to Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>Preachers,</hi> as it is in the Act of Toleration, 24 <hi>May,</hi> 89. <hi>prim. Guliel. &amp; Mar.</hi> This has render'd our Church a perfect <hi>Cypher:</hi> And if any, or all, of our Flocks ſhould Deſert us to morrow, and go over open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> we have no Power left us, by this Act, to reſtrain any of them by <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Cenſures,</hi> or any other way; and the whole Nation have Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to believe any of their Communions to be as ſafe a way to Heaven as our own. And they have made full uſe of that Liberty: For how many do we meet with who do not believe it? And think it a thing indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent which of our <hi>Churches</hi> they go to, as they term the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> and ours. They think them all to be <hi>Churches;</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving equal <hi>Liberty</hi> to <hi>All,</hi> who dare quarrel with any for taking that Liberty to go to <hi>Any</hi> or <hi>All</hi> of theſe Churches?</p>
            <p>Who can ſay the <hi>Parliament</hi> has done Ill? For if <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> be not <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> why are they bound to ſet it up more than <hi>Presbytery, Independency, Quakeriſm,</hi> or any other Sort? Why have we made ſuch Conteſts about it, theſe Ages paſt?</p>
            <p>But if it be <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> then it is out of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Power to <hi>Aboliſh</hi> it; or even to <hi>Diſpence</hi> with, or <hi>Tolerate,</hi> any other Form of <hi>Government</hi> in the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that we muſt either Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn what they have done in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and in <hi>England</hi> too, by this <hi>Toleration;</hi> or otherwiſe we
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97419:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
muſt give up our <hi>Jure Divino</hi> Right, which we have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to hold out ſo long againſt the <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> and profeſs to hold <hi>hereafter</hi> by no other Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure than that of an <hi>Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> which now Grants equal Liberty to the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> as to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>But this Law does not only proclaim <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Indemnity,</hi> but propoſes <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages</hi> to all who ſhall leave us. Any, of any Sort, <hi>in Orders</hi> or <hi>out of Orders,</hi> who pleaſe to ſet up for <hi>Teachers,</hi> are, by this Act, <hi>exempted from ſerving upon Juries, or from being Church war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, Overſeers of the Poor, or any other Parochial or Ward Office, or other Office in any Hundred of any Shire, City, Town, Pariſh, Diviſion, or Wapentake.</hi> And theſe being Offices of <hi>Charge</hi> and <hi>Trouble,</hi> we ſhall be in a little time left to ſerve our ſelves; or the whole Burthen lie upon thoſe Few whom their Neighbours will call Fools for not eaſing themſelves of it, as they have done. The Effect of this may not appear conſiderably at firſt: But when the Taxes have Reduc'd more to Poverty; and the Envy and Spite to ſee their richer Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours excuſed, may operate more than we are yet well aware. If you think that no ſuch Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable People will be allow'd of for <hi>Preachers:</hi> The Act ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts none. And the Allowance is Granted to the <hi>Juſtices of Peace:</hi> And there is no ſtint of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. I can tell you an Inſtance came in my way at the <hi>Eaſter</hi> Seſſions 92. in St. <hi>Albans;</hi> there came three poor Fellows for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences to be <hi>Preachers,</hi> Two of them ſet their Marks inſtead of their Names, for they could neither Read nor Write, and they had their <hi>Licences:</hi> And one of them being after Return'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Jury, pleaded his Privilege as a <hi>Preacher</hi> by the Act, and had it allow'd him. Nor indeed can the Juſtices Refuſe either to give them Licences, or allow them the <hi>Privileges</hi> granted by the Act. One of theſe <hi>Preachers</hi> Names, I remember, was one <hi>Bocket;</hi> he lives in St. <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Pariſh near St. <hi>Albans,</hi> and is a <hi>Ditcher,</hi> and <hi>Day-Labourer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many ſuch Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples through the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>We may now ſee where our Authority is going, not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> at this Rate. That <hi>Bocket</hi> is now as Legal a <hi>Teacher</hi> as the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi> This, Brother, is a fair Indication of the <hi>Inclinations</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> towards us, of their Zeal to ſupport the <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> and the <hi>Reputation</hi> of our <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well: But they have left us in Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Rents</hi> and <hi>Revenues</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97419:14"/>That is indeed <hi>All</hi> that we have left. And how long ſhall we keep that, when the only Ground and Foundation of it is gone? that is, The <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the Church, and the ſuppoſed <hi>Neceſſity</hi> there is of <hi>our Church.</hi> This is all the Ground and Reaſon there is for ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and maintaining <hi>our Church</hi> more than <hi>any other Church;</hi> or for having <hi>any Church</hi> more than <hi>no Church.</hi> If none of them be <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> or <hi>ours</hi> no more than <hi>another,</hi> why ſhould we expect to Enjoy ſuch great <hi>Riches</hi> more than others? The Nation is not, or ſoon may come not to be, in a Condition to allow ſuch great <hi>Penſions,</hi> when they are meerly <hi>Honorary,</hi> and of no Neceſſity to the Nation.</p>
            <p>The Biſhops Lands (as now in <hi>Scotland</hi>) may be ſold, either for the Carrying on the War, or to Reward many of thoſe Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and <hi>Sacrament taking Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> for Places of Advantage. There is no other viſible Fund for them; and they Expect it; and refrain not ſometimes to Expreſs it. Our Titles being <hi>Jure Divino</hi> will not do: The <hi>Impropriations</hi> have ſpoil'd that. The Church, though over-run with Errors, was in far greater <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Reverence</hi> than now, when <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth ſeized her <hi>Revenue;</hi> and had more and greater Friends to ſtand by her: The <hi>Pope,</hi> and all the then <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes,</hi> did Deteſt his Act as <hi>Sacrilegious,</hi> and were highly Concern'd to have it Rectified. And it was thought abominable by all <hi>England,</hi> except thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom he Divided the Spoil. But is there one Man in the World would be Concern'd for us, or Pity us, if we loſt all! Yet the <hi>Inclinations of the People</hi> is all we pretend to Truſt to. How have I heard ſome repeat with Pleaſure, that Prophecy which they aſcribe to old <hi>Merlin?</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth pull'd down <hi>Abbys</hi> and <hi>Cells;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But <hi>Henry</hi> the Ninth will pull down <hi>Churches and Bells.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Bells</hi> they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>Epiſcopal Church</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> and there has been enough done in <hi>Scotland</hi> to fulfil the Prophecy, but that it was ſpoke of <hi>England.</hi> And they think that <hi>Henry</hi> the Ninth, and the time is now come. I lay not ſtreſs upon theſe ſort of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, but they ſhew the <hi>Inclinations of the People,</hi> when they are <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> and no body <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> with Trumping up ſuch ſtuff up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us.</p>
            <p>Add to this whatever ſtreſs you will lay upon the confident Boaſting of thoſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> who are moſt in K. <hi>Will</hi>'s Intereſt and Councils, that all will be their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97419:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
own they make no doubt of it; only they would manage, as they think, wiſely, and worm us out by Degrees. They told us, from the Beginning of this <hi>Revolution,</hi> that K. <hi>William</hi> would take his time to bring them into the chief Places and Offices of Truſt; which we Thought, in our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Month, to be nothing but the vain Humour of that Party, and to create Jealouſies betwixt the King and us, when we were endeavoring to exceed one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our Careſſes; which if they were meant no more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely on his ſide than they were by ſome of us, it was a Force on both ſides; and not like longer to laſt, than the firſt Opportunity either could get to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into hands they could bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Truſt.</p>
            <p>They told us too, That he would begin with <hi>Scotland,</hi> and according to the Succeſs he had there would take his Meaſures as to <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is not a Step has been made, which they have not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and truly foretold. It is eaſy for <hi>Managers</hi> to be <hi>Prophets</hi> of what is <hi>deſign'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wiſh what is to Come of their <hi>Prediction,</hi> may not prove as True as what is Paſt. That is, That, having Divided the <hi>Church of England</hi> among themſelves, they would, through Fears or Hopes, gain the major Number to come over to their Doctrine of <hi>Reſiſtance;</hi> whereby, having proclaimed themſelves to have been Falſe-Teachers heretofore, they would eaſily prevail with the People not to Truſt them for the time to come: And ſo, by conſequence gain the Cry on their ſide, and have their turn in ſetting up upon the <hi>Inclinations of the Peoples;</hi> and overturn Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy <hi>here,</hi> as they have done in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Indifferency</hi> in <hi>Lovers</hi> is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Forerunner of a <hi>Breach.</hi> And the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> who were ſo exceſſively Enamour'd of us, when the <hi>Biſhops</hi> were in the <hi>Tower,</hi> that they hardly forbore to <hi>Worſhip</hi> us, are now, I wiſh I could ſay but <hi>Cool,</hi> and <hi>very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> towards us.</p>
            <p>What the End of all theſe Things will be, is what, dear Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, has tortur'd my Thoughts, and makes me vent them ſo freely to you, who, I know, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, in a great meaſure, in them with my ſelf.</p>
            <p>But, O good God! If we have not been Sincere with Him, he knows our Hearts! If Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Advantages have been any Biaſs to us! Or if, as <hi>Uzzah,</hi> we have put forth our hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our own Rank and Order, going but in the leaſt out of the plain Road of our Duty, tho, as we thought, to ſave the <hi>Ark</hi> from falling, oh! what will our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97419:15"/>
be! if thoſe Methods we have taken to preſerve the <hi>Church,</hi> prove, as it ſadly now threatens, to her and our own utter De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction! We ſee the Enemy already <hi>Roar in the midſt of our Congregations, and they have ſet up their Banners for a Token:</hi> We ſeem now to hold our Poſt but at their Diſcretion, till they are ready to give the Word, as in <hi>Scotland,</hi> No more <hi>Epiſcopacy!</hi> No more <hi>Church of England!</hi> But we ſhall not fall like them: They fell altogether, every <hi>Biſhop</hi> in the Kingdom, and almoſt the whole Number of the inferiour Clergy. They may riſe again, and will riſe Glorious, aſſerting ſtill the ſame Principles as we did before in the Reſtoration, 1660. But as for us now, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall we cauſe our Shame to go?</hi> Will not the <hi>Scots</hi> upbraid us? Where was our Zeal for <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,</hi> or Foreſight of our own Danger, when we ſtood ſilent by, and ſaw their Fall, without putting in one Addreſs, or ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leaſt Concern for our Brethren? They will mind us (for we have not thought of it) of the Zeal which the <hi>Engliſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> ſhew'd in the Caſe of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> unjuſtly Depriv'd by <hi>Lay-Authority</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, though there was an <hi>Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> there to countenance it; they Eſpous'd it as their own Cauſe (for ſo indeed it was) till they prevail'd with the King to have him Reſtor'd. But now we could ſee not only all the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> in that Kingdom, but our own Renowned <hi>Metropolitan,</hi> and near half of the then <hi>Biſhops</hi> of our own Kingdom, Depriv'd by meer <hi>Lay-Authority,</hi> (not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Diſpute of the Validity of that <hi>Lay Authority,</hi> and the Cauſe, which none of us did think ſufficient for a Depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) without Interpoſing one Word on their behalf; or ſo much as for having that Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance made good to them which was provided for them by the Act of Parliament, either by K. <hi>William</hi> to whom the Act en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted the Diſpoſing of it; or if not from his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> yet at leaſt from the <hi>Generoſity</hi> of thoſe who came, Unwilling and Sorrowful, as they pretended, into their Places. Nor did our <hi>Convocation</hi> once complain of the Abſence of their <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> and ſo many of their other <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or make any Addreſs on their behalf, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire any Conference with them, to know their Reaſons, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour any Accommodation. No; we did none of theſe things: We were ſeized with, I know not what, panick Conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Though all were well In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd, and every one would gladly have been a <hi>Second,</hi> yet none durſt <hi>Begin.</hi> We were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97419:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Paſſive</hi> here to a ſuperlative De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: Our Courage and our Souls have left us. We lie under the Load, though we ſee our ſelves ſinking with it. What is this but <hi>Infatuation!</hi> and the End muſt be <hi>Deſtruction.</hi> But now, at laſt, if we have any Spirit left; though we have not made any Addreſs, or ſhewn our ſelves Concern'd for the Caſe of our Brethren in <hi>Scotland,</hi> or for our Depriv'd Biſhops and Clergy <hi>here;</hi> yet let us not ſit ſtill, and, by a ſupine Negligence, be ſo wanting to <hi>our ſelves,</hi> as at leaſt not to Petition, to Repreſent our Fears and our Danger to the King and Government, to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſome Redreſs to our juſt Grievances; That there may be an Alteration of the Perſons em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in publick Offices, and ſuch only ſet at the Head of Affairs as are ſincerely for the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and let us make our Exceptions againſt thoſe whom we know to be of a quite different Intereſt. We ventur'd upon all this, and more, to King <hi>James,</hi> and had good Succeſs in it. Who knows but upon our appearing Zealous and Active for the Safety of the <hi>Church,</hi> others of our Flocks may joyn with us? At leaſt, they will Approve and Juſtify us in aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>our</hi> and <hi>their</hi> true Intereſt. But who will ſtir for us, or ſtand by us, if we Dare not ſo much as open our Mouths in our own Behalf? It is our Office to Lead and Inſtruct them: They will love us the better for it. And we may, by this, Recover ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whom we have loſt. But we ſhall looſe all, if we Render our ſelves wholy Inſignificant and Inſenſible of the Encroachments which are daily made upon us: And our Poſterities may curſe us, in whoſe Power it was to have ſtem'd this Tide, if we had taken it in time. The People will never believe that we can be hearty to them, and ſtand in the Gap for preſervation of their Rights and Privileges (as we have heretofore done, and were Honour'd for it) while they ſee us ſo very Diſpirited and Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in our own.</p>
            <p>At leaſt this we ſhall Gain by it, That if a Deaf Ear be given to all our Applications, we may then reſt aſſur'd of what is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd againſt us.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>17 <hi>July,</hi> 1694.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
